I made a data dir following the recommendation of the book “Python Text Processing with NLTK 2.0 Cookbook” https://www.packtpub.com/article/python-text-processing-nltk-20-creating-custom-corpora as shown below:NLTK defines a list of data directories, or paths, in nltk.data.path. Our custom corpora must be within one of these paths so it can be found by NLTK. So as not to conflict with the official data package, we'll create a custom nltk_data directory in our home directory. Here's some Python code to create this directory and verify that it is in the list of known paths specified by nltk.data.path:>>> import os, os.path >>> path = os.path.expanduser('~/nltk_data') >>> if not os.path.exists(path): ...    os.mkdir(path) >>> os.path.exists(path) True >>> import nltk.data >>> path in nltk.data.path TrueThen C:\Documents and Settings\frey\Application Data\nltk_data\corpora\senseval (on Windows) is created, the corpora dir will have about 50 listed.Delete everything from the senseval dir (about 5 .pos files) and copy the new senseval-3 files into that same dir. I named the senseval-3 files  .pos, even though they don’t have pos tags (senseval-2 had pos and word sense <head> tags). That’s because the senseval import looks for .pos files for each word.Then you can import the files like so:>>> from nltk.corpus import senseval>>> senseval.fileids()['sense_activate.v.pos', 'sense_add.v.pos', 'sense_appear.v.pos', 'sense_argument.n.pos', 'sense_arm.n.pos', 'sense_ask.v.pos', 'sense_atmosphere.n.pos', 'sense_audience.n.pos']>>> senseval.instances('sense_activate.v.pos')[SensevalInstance(word='activate.v', position=55, context=['Do', 'you', 'know', 'what', 'it', 'is', ',', 'and', 'where', 'I', 'can', 'get', 'one', '?', 'We', 'suspect', 'you', 'had', 'seen', 'the', 'Terrex', 'Autospade', ',', 'which', 'is', …One thing to note if we write a new import, some training examples list a word with multiple senses, unlike our previous pos tagging, where one word would have one tag. An example like so:<instance id="ask.v.bnc.00000105" docsrc="BNC"><answer instance="ask.v.bnc.00000105" senseid="238102"/><context>What if I find certain issues or situations difficult ?  Your course leader will be available to help you .  You are also <head>asked</head> to keep your church leaders informed of your involvement so that they can ensure you are adequately supported . After every client visit you are asked to call the office so that you can report how the visit went .  We also hold regular meetings of volunteers to discuss issues of concern and encourage one another .  </context></instance><instance id="ask.v.bnc.00000106" docsrc="BNC"><answer instance="ask.v.bnc.00000106" senseid="238102"/><answer instance="ask.v.bnc.00000106" senseid="238103"/><context>Your course leader will be available to help you .  You are also asked to keep your church leaders informed of your involvement so that they can ensure you are adequately supported .  After every client visit you are <head>asked</head> to call the office so that you can report how the visit went . We also hold regular meetings of volunteers to discuss issues of concern and encourage one another .  Volunteers visiting an ACET client have immediate access to professional nursing support through our 24 hour on call facility .  </context></instance>Note that the first one has one sense (238102), while the second one has two senses (with just a single word tagged).